foreign
[Music]
I've talked about sunscreen and topical
retinoids what other skin cream
components have been shown to help with
skin aging while placebo-controlled
trials are the standard and most medical
research they're still all too rare for
cosmetic products this raises efficacy
questions many are left with simply
buying hope in a jar as well as safety
concerns Cosmetics to this day contain
an array of toxic chemicals of the more
than 12 000 synthetic chemicals used in
cosmetics fewer than 20 percent have
been recognized as safe
of course this doesn't mean natural
ingredients are necessarily harmless
poison ivy is as natural as you can get
but you wouldn't want to rub it on your
face
however there are some relatively safe
natural options with varying degrees of
efficacy in contrast to retinoic acid a
form of vitamin A that can be irritating
topical niacinamide also known as
nicotinamide is a form of vitamin B3
that is non-irritating and found to be
effective it's been described as one of
the best studied cosmeceutical
ingredients for anti-aging but it looks
like there are only two
placebo-controlled human studies which
gives you an idea of the state of
cosmeceutical science
skin photo aging is largely needed by UV
induced free radical formation one of
the consequences of excess sun exposure
is the oxidation of sugars and proteins
in the skin into yellow brown pigments
that give aging skin a yellowing sallow
appearance since niacinamide is a
precursor to two potent antioxidants the
hope is that this process could be
interrupted and indeed the first
published study was entitled topical
niacinamide reduces yellowing wrinkling
red blotchiness and hyperpigmented spots
in aging facial skin it was a 12 week
double blind placebo-controlled
randomized clinical split face study of
middle-aged women in a split face study
each woman is her own control rubbing
the active formulation in this case five
percent niacinamide and moisturizer on
one side of her face and the placebo
straight moisturizer on the other half
though neither She nor the researchers
know which side is which until the code
is broken at the end this controls for
skin type and administer technique and
different people apply facial products
differently but participants often use
the same hand for applying the creams to
both sides so unless specified that
different gloves be worn or hands washed
in between there can be
cross-contamination anyway at the end of
12 weeks there was a small five percent
reduction in wrinkles and fine lines and
slowing the development of blotchiness
spots
and salonist
a subsequent publication noted an
improvement in skin elasticity as well
the magnitude of these effects may only
be one-third to one-fifth as good as
retinoic acid but there were no reports
of excess skin irritation
but use the four percent concentration
and application was limited to crow's
feet wrinkles around the eyes
significant reductions in wrinkles by
both subjective and objective measures
were noted by the end of the eight week
study 64 of the niacinamide side eye
wrinkles on when moderate or Market
Improvement compared to zero percent on
the placebo side eyes
oh